What I want to say is that I think that what I call Christian atheism is still the ethical stance which fits today's predicament.
Okay, let me begin with a a simple observation.
Those who follow obscure spiritual cosmological speculations have for sure heard of one of the most popular topics in this domain.
You know all these mythical stories that when three planets, usually Earth, Moon and the Sun, find themselves along the same axis,
then some big cataclysmic event takes place, the whole order of the universe is momentarily thrown out of join, and the universe has to find a new balance.
You remember that it wasn't taken seriously, but the panic of 2012, where idea is to some
Maya, old Mayan predictions precisely because I think Earth, Moon and Sun were in the same line. It's not good.
And I think that politically something like this holds for this year, 2017, which is a triple anniversary.
In 2017, we do not celebrate only the centenary of the October Revolution, 1917, but also
the 150th anniversary of the first edition of Marxist Capital, 1867, and maybe the most tragic event,
the 50th anniversary of the so-called Shanghai Commune, when in the climactic moment of the Chinese great proletarian cultural revolution.
It's a wonderful moment, maybe the crucial moment of 20th century communism.
Residents of Shanghai, workers and students,
decided to take literally Mao's call, you know when Mao said attack the headquarters,
You don't need neither the party nor the army.
People should take over.
Well, they took this literally and simply overthrew offices, destroy of local communist party, ignored the army, and took over.
And that was the crucial point because then Mao had to send the army.
and it's an extremely tragic event because this was then, people don't know this, the biggest battle of the Cultural Revolution.
Forget about, okay, they were tragic, all those things, you know, red guard discs pulling their beard, terrorizing professors, intellectuals, all that.
No, it was the battle for Shanghai when the army turned on the very revolutionaries.
And one don't know how many the idea is that it goes into tens, if not hundreds of thousands of dead people.
But I think this event is fascinating because I don't like this big question, was Mao since here or not?
At a certain level, he was not.
It's clearly that he triggered the Cultural Revolution to regain his full power in the army, sorry, in the state.
But it doesn't matter if Mao was manipulating.
Things ran out of control.
Ordinary workers took it seriously.
Let's have directly the rule of the community.
We don't need the party, we don't need the army and so on, and it went too far.
So I think these three events mark the three stages of the communist movement.
First, capital by Marx outlined the theoretical foundations of the communist revolution.
Then the October revolution was the first successful attempt to overthrow bourgeois state and build a new social economic order.
And then the Shanghai commune stands for the most radical attempt to immediately realize the most daring aspect of the communist vision,
the abolishment of state power and the imposition of direct people's power organized as a network of local communities.
It didn't work, and of course, I will not answer the question today, namely the big question, what went wrong?
I think, that's my hypothesis, what went wrong with this cycle?
Perhaps the answer is to be solved, and people don't talk about it, but for me at least, as a Christian, it is the key date.
Don't you know that today we have another, We have four planets in the line. Another mega anniversary.
2017 is the 500 years anniversary of 1517 when Martin Luther put on that door the 95 thesis, Protestantism.
And I still think that Protestantism is the key, the greatest religious event that you can imagine.
Why?
Let me begin in a very simplified way,
but I'm not totally bluffing, because I presented a version of this text at a theological colloquium in Cambridge, and it went well.
What can I say?
So I'm not totally bluffing.
I'm not totally bluffing.
Let me begin by this triad of orthodoxy, Catholicism, and Protestantism.
The way I see it, maybe I'm wrong,
central to the Orthodox tradition is the notion of theosis, of man becoming like God,
or to quote Saint Athanasius of Alexandria, quote,
she, Christ, or God, was incarnate so that we might be made God, end of quote.
What should otherwise seem absurd,
that fallen sinful men may become holy as God is holy has been made possible through Jesus Christ who is God incarnate.
And then Saint Maximus the Confessor wrote in the same vein, again a quote,
a sure warrant for looking with hope to deification of human nature is provided by the incarnation of God,
which makes man God to the same degree as God himself became man.
Let us become the image of the one whole God,
bearing nothing earthly in ourselves,
so that we may consort with God and become gods,
receiving from God our existence as gods, end of quote.
This orthodox formula, God became man, so that man becomes God,
is, I think, what Protestantism radically rejects.
The deepest insight of Protestantism, although it's implicit already in the Bible, is that, to put it very simply,
God become man and that's it, nothing more.
Everything already happens in the incarnation.
What needs to be added is just a shift of perspective.
I think that in authentic Christian vision, there is no resurrection to follow.
Holy ghost already is resurrection.
Resurrection happens in the Christian community.
God dies and he remains dead.
We are condemned to freedom.
Holy community is not, there is, I read here, Christianity in a radically atheist way.
Holy ghost is not some kind of a synthesis.
God, man, and then they are brought together.
No, with crucifixion, precisely that type of God, you know, this primitive idea.
Up there, there is a great old guy with a long beard who takes care of us, so don't worry too much.
Ultimately, we are taken care of.
That's what Hegel, my favorite, puts it nicely.
He says, what dies on the cross is not an earthly representative of God.
It's God himself, that God of beyond.
So what remains?
We in our freedom.
And that would be the properly Christian trick.
I say God gave us all freedom and so on.
He said, but he didn't.
God abandoned, he just creates that and let us alone, God abandoned us.
I'll say, but that's another name for freedom.
You should just shift the perspective.
Or to put it in another way, and I'm here, I am basing my reading on some very good theologies from my beloved Chesterton onwards.
In other religions, to simplify it very much, you have got men.
We have fallen from God.
So the idea is let's climb back to some stupid spiritual exercises, whatever you want.
Like let's get rid of our sinful nature.
go back to God the Christian solution is a totally different one it is this one
okay let's say you an ordinary believer find yourself totally abandoned by God
so what's the way out of it not okay let me do some good works or self-punishment to become clean no it's that at that point when I'm totally abandoned by God
I identify with Christ who finds himself in exactly the same position with the famous Father, Father have you forsaken me.
So that it's a wonderful insight that you should see in a very Hegelian way how our separation, we overcome our separation from God, not by rejoining God, but by realizing that this separation is sepa
That at that point, we are divine.
Because again, the ultimate moment of divinity is that moment of, as Gilbert Keith Chesterton put it, the moment when God himself becomes an atheist.
You know, because remember, on the cross, when Christ says, Elie Elie lama sabachthami gavadar, he for a brief moment becomes a non-believer.
which is a crazy moment.
You find this in no other religion.
In other religions, you do find men who abandon God.
Where do you find God who abandons himself?
And again, the Christian solution is not you suffer, you are low, but don't worry, there are good news.
No, there are no good news.
Good news are only a different shift of perspective on the bad news.
We remain abandoned by God.
God will not come to save us.
As even conservative theologists who are not stupid knew, like Paul Plodel, my favorite French conservative Catholic, he says very nicely that the ultimate secret of Christianity is not trust God.
Things may look bad, but God will help you.
No, it's the opposite.
God needs our help.
Only we can save God.
In other words, the divine, and some theosophic speculation, I will not go into it, we don't have time to lose here,
develop this in a wonderful way where they claim that the secret of reincarnation is not that God did something heroic to redeem us.
God, God without incarnation is not fully God.
God incarnates himself in man to become fully God.
That's the solution of one of my favorite, apart from Hegel, German idealist Schelling, who developed in his Heidegger claim, know that these two texts, especially Freichheitschrift,
who developed in his Heidegger claim, know that these two texts, especially Freichheitschrift,
Schelling's text on the essence of human freedom,
and later Weltalter fragments on the ages of the world,
he developed this how God produced logos, gave birth to Logos' son, Schelling literally said this, to save himself from his own madness.
It was, if I may be cynical, a kind of, you know, psychiatrists say if you are caught in psychosis, you need creative therapy, you know, through work.
Well, that's what God did.
And some very, if you think I'm bluffing,
some very intelligent Protestant theologists came to the same conclusion.
Like, a Norwegian friend of mine gave me a reference and he translated some parts to me because it's not a well-known book, famous only in Norway.
The guy's name is Peter Wessel Zakve, a book on Protestantism God.
It's a reading of Book of Job.
And you know what's his reading?
What does Job discover when he encounters God, when he realizes that God is doing very strange things, punishing him for nothing, and so on?
Here is a quote from Zapfel, Job finds himself confronted with a world ruler, God, of grotesque primitiveness,
a cosmic cave-dweller, a braggart and blusterer, almost agreeable in his total ignorance of spiritual culture.
What is new for Job is not God's greatness in quantifiable terms, that we knew fully in advance.
What is new is God's qualitative baseness.
And I think this is masked insight also of the big Protestant topic of predestination.
You mean God was simply playing a brutal game with us, he didn't care.
God decided in advance, you are redeemed, you are lost, totally irrespective of what we are doing.
And I think this is the right line.
I think that, as intelligent Protestants saw it, this Catholic way of linking our salvation to our good works introduces immediately an element of handling, of financial transaction.
I see that child drowning, should I do it or not, well, I may gain salvation, so fuck it, why not do it, you know?
It makes our good deeds part of a almost, I would say, financial investment into future.
But as Luther put it very intelligently, if there is predestination, then the solution is pure goodness.
Because you see a child drowning, sorry for this pathetic example, and you know very well that it will not help your salvation in any way if you help the child or not.
So it's only goodness that makes you do it.
So let's go on here.
In this position where the solution is not some kind of a reunification of God with men,
We overcome our alienation of God through a simple realization that God is already alienated from himself, self-abandoned.
I like to apply here to divinity Hegel's wonderful reading of ancient Greek statues which are impenetrable for us, like what does the Sphinx mean?
And you know what's Hegel's formula.
The secrets of ancient Greeks, secrets for us, were already secrets for ancient Greeks themselves.
And Hegel's theology is precisely this one, that the secrets of divinity are secrets also for divinity itself.
This is the old mystical topic.
Hegel goes there into that line.
You find it in Meister Eckhart and all other guys that to bring history into God himself,
what happens on our earth, our theological activity, decides the fate of God himself in a way.
It's the other way around.
It's not that God decides, no.
We in our struggles, we fight for the fate of God himself.
So how to bring this, and now it comes, maybe it will be a little bit difficult, the proper theological point.
I think I improvised a little bit already in my classes about this.
Does this mean that Protestantism simply abolishes our freedom?
Everyone who knows Luther, and I don't have the time to go into it, but I have it written,
a detailed analysis of the tension between Martin Luther and, of course, Thomas Münzer, the great theologist of the German peasant revolt.
Maybe this will surprise you, but I'm almost more on the early Luther's side.
He was right, Münzer, in criticizing Luther for his confirmation taking the side of the masters, and so on.
But Mincer, I think, comes all too close, then,
to this perverse instrumental position which comes close to totalitarianism.
Because Luther was right, and this was his greatest theological insight, to insist on divine impenetrability,
which, written in a materialist way, doesn't mean God knows what he is doing, we just cannot penetrate it.
It means that quote from Sapwe, God is crazy, doesn't know it.
So Luther warned against precisely what we call today fundamentalism.
Any position of an agent, historical, who, my God, what is happening here?
I'm getting superstitious. Yesterday it was one, at least they are not black cats and we will survive there.
But it's the Maoist movement, one divides into two.
Okay, sorry, let's go on, that Luther comes too close to this, seeing his political movement as direct instrument of the divine will, and this is what Luther is right to prohibit.
She insists on this radical impenetrability, there is predestination, but we never know what is predestination.
Like our lives are decided in advance, but we cannot ever know it.
So it's absolutely prohibited to claim I am an instrument of the divine will, like the Stalinist communists in a different way, historical necessity of progress towards communism runs through me.
No, we cannot do it.
And I think this is authentic freedom.
This idea of my life is predestined, but I don't know what it is.
So this terrible struggle to make the right decision.
Because you know, here common sense doesn't work.
Because common sense would tell us, why do you worry?
If there is predestination, sit down and masturbate and watch hardcore movies, it doesn't matter.
No, the idea is that this also, that it doesn't work, explains, we all know it, I'm even repeating myself, I think years ago, I was already selling this here, I'm sorry,
because this also explains this paradox of predestination and freedom, explains the greatest mystery of this old Max Weber thesis, why is Protestantism as a religion which is based on predestination,
Why Protestantism became the religious background, at least originally, of capitalism, which is precisely the most active social system, a system where you are solicited to be active like crazy all the time.
Again, wouldn't it be logical to claim, if it's predestined, fuck off, I lay down, awaken me when God comes, but leave me alone.
Weber saw this clearly and Luther, that precisely because you don't know it, knowing that your faith is decided but not knowing what your faith is, pushes you to incessant activity
and I think that this decision, this difficult decision to discover if there is predestination,
faith necessity, what is that faith, is much closer to authentic freedom than, I'm using no metaphor that already used, I'm sorry for my students in my class,
then this simple freedom of, I go to a patisserie, they have strawberry cake, chocolate cake, vanilla cake, or which one I will choose, you know, this simple freedom of choice.
No, true freedom is this one, and even now you will say I'm crazy.
But let me give you an example to repeat that already given my class.
Think about love, the choice of object in love.
It must be free, if not, it's not love, of course, no?
But it never happens to you, admit it, as a free choice.
If you say, oh, now I will fall in love into that lady or man, it's fake.
It is a free decision, but as Schelling put it, a transcendental, a temporal free decision which you experience precisely as its opposite, as your fate.
You experience love as, my God, I cannot escape it, I'm caught into it.
And that's true freedom.
That's the radical freedom.
Now you will say, this is sentimental speculation.
No, I'll use another example from my class.
Isn't it exactly the same with a tough political decision?
Not the simple decisions, vote for Macron, vote for Le Pen with Puff, I don't care.
But let's make a pathetic example.
There is war, my country is attacked, and I have to decide will I risk my life, do it or not.
This is a free decision by me.
But if you take the difficult decision that you will fight, you don't experience it as a choice.
You experience it, I would love not to do it, but it's my duty, I cannot not do it.
I have to do it.
And I think this provides this wonderful dialectic described, as far as I know, by philosophy
only nicely, clearly only by Hegel, how predestination is much more paradoxical if we read Protestantism
in a materialist way than the simple notion, there is predestination, everything is decided no.
means we have a faith, but we retroactively create this faith.
Like I freely decide something and once I decide it, it retroactively becomes necessary.
If I do the right thing, I experienced it my God, I couldn't do it otherwise, I had to do it.
That's freedom.
So that's my first point about Protestantism.
Which means that not only you are free, but you are even more free than you thought.
You are even responsible for your fate, for your necessity.
And again, as I already explained in my classes, here psychoanalysis rejoins Protestantism.
Because in psychoanalysis, the obvious result is something like predestination.
You know, like, I think I'm a free being, but no, everything is predetermined through my past traumas, through whatever, you know, so I discover that I'm not free.
And this was the fashionable lesson half a century ago with that fashion of structuralism in France.
This is how psychoanalysis was read, structural psychoanalysis.
You think you are a free subject, no. You are just a puppet, the big other, the symbolic order, runs the game, and so on.
But look, Lacan follows here Freud, yes, you are over-determined, but you cannot use this over-determination or psychic necessity which makes you what you are.
You cannot use it as an excuse, you know, like, to be vulgar, I'm sorry.
I rape a child and then I say to the judges, sorry guys, what can I do?
I was over determined by my unconscious complex.
No, you are predestined by fate, but you are responsible even for that.
You are much more radically responsible.
And I can't go into it now, I already did it in my class to develop how the same goes also for, that's why it's a great thing, Kantian ethics.
And Kant says, do Kant then do souls.
You can do it because you must do it.
Like no excuse to not do your duty.
If it's your duty, you have to do it.
But Kant, this is not so often noticed, goes even a step further.
He also implies that even doing your duty cannot be an excuse for doing your duty.
Like Chris, I hate you, let me do it.
I have to do something, it's my duty which will hurt you.
I don't have the right to tell you, sorry guy, but it's my duty.
No, I don't have the right to externalize it.
I'm not responsible only to do my duty.
I have to fully subjectively assume also my duty in the sense of what is my duty.
This is why incidentally, I mentioned this briefly in my class, and now I will stop with plagiarizing myself.
Don't worry, I will not repeat my class.
This is why I think that although I admire her, at some point in her otherwise wonderful
Eichmann in Jerusalem, if I remember it correctly, Hannah Arendt was wrong.
When she took seriously Eichmann's statement that she was just a good Kantian.
He did his duty for him, duty was embodied in Führer's orders, so sorry I was doing my duty.
No, Eichmann did precisely the wrong thing.
He was not a Kantian because he did something that Kant strictly prohibits.
He used duty as an excuse, sorry, I kept killing millions of Jews, what can I do, that's my duty.
No, you cannot refer to your duty as some objective determination that you have just to follow.
You are radically responsible for your duties.
Now I will complicate things.
Now the end of self-pluggerizing.
You will get some new stuff.
This solution, this dialectical interconnection of necessity and freedom, where, yes, there is necessity,
but this necessity is, in a deeper sense, contingent.
Like, you do something in a contingent way.
Once you do it, it retroactively becomes your fate.
This solution works only on one condition.
The subject, believer, agent, is absolutely constrained by the horizon of his or her finite subjectivity.
What Protestantism prohibits is the very thought that as a believer, I can, as it were,
took a position outside, above myself, and looked upon myself as a small particle in the vast reality.
Here since I already mentioned Mao Zedong, I would like to criticize him a little bit
at the philosophical level and incidentally because of some of my lines like this, Alain Badiou is even now mad at me, you know.
Mao Zedong, I think, was wrong when he deployed his Olympic vision, reducing human experience to a tiny, unimportant cosmic detail.
You know, in his famous statement where he say we don't fear atomic war and so on, okay, with that I in principle agree.
But Mao went on and said this, a quote from Mao Zedong, the United States cannot annihilate the Chinese nation with its small stack of atom bombs.
Even if the US atom bombs were so powerful that, when dropped on China, they would make a hole right through the earth, or even blew the earth up, that would hardly mean anything
to the universe as a whole, though it might be a major event for the solar system.
You know, it's kind of a weird excuse.
OK, Americans can destroy us, but what does it mean from the standpoint of the universe or whatever?
I think that this argument, Mao's, only works if in a pseudo-Kantian way.
We presuppose, like, the problem is, where is Mao speaking from what subjective position when he states this.
He acts as if he speaks from a totally external, purely divine position where you see objectively reality in human eyes, and then you can say,
okay, our Earth is blown apart, fuck it, a tiny blimp in some small planet, who cares?
But here I don't have time to develop it, but this is beautiful theological topic.
Intelligent Protestantism have a wonderful vision where it's again that link between contingency and necessity.
On the one hand, yes, we are a tiny piece of feet in a vast universe.
Protestantism is not ethnocentric, which is why Protestantism in so far as it stands for modernity was precisely the religious background of modern science, which precisely introduced the objective view of reality.
You know that before Protestantism, the medieval world was earth in the center, although we
humans were not the center of the universe, it was God, but nonetheless, we were the highest point of the created universe, everything turned around us, and so on and so on.
So what Protestantism unites, I don't have time to develop it now just to give an idea, is I think something wonderful.
At the same time, this extremely brutal view.
From an inhuman gaze, we are nothing.
A tiny species on Earth, it doesn't matter.
But nonetheless, since we cannot ever really assume that view, external view, in our ethical practice,
we have to act as if whenever, and Kant puts it this very nicely, although objective science is telling us that fuck it, we are again one tiny piece of dust in the universe,
Nonetheless, in a big ethical struggle, it's not just our fate that is decided, as it were, can't put it so nicely, the entire universe was created as a background for that struggle of ours.
You know, I love this unity of extreme ethnocentrism.
The world was created so that we can fight this battle, and this radically external view.
Because this is, in a way, when you witness a big change, a revolution or whatever, even
with Holocaust, I think the intelligent argument, even Habermas made it, who tries to be a rationalist,
but Habermas, I don't agree with him, made once a nice point where he says that with Holocaust, and I would add nonetheless some other events, like what happened in Congo, other horrible things and so on.
Something so horrible happens that you in a way diminish its horror when you reduce it to a simple human event.
Something went wrong in class struggle, whatever, it's horrible to say Holocaust was just a sub-chapter in class struggle and effort and so on.
Something that Habermas says very intelligently that theological dimension means here just a way, a specific way, to signal that something so horrible happened that it doesn't fit our universe.
We cannot, I'll put it this way, we cannot simply renormalize it as just another historical event.
That's why, isn't this the title, you may correct me, maybe you know it more, of one of the books on Holocaust, The Black Sun, the sun itself turned out, you know, like Like as some people say nicely, when something like Holocaust happened, it's a shame that the world continued to exist.
If there were to be an elementary ethic in the world, out of shame the world should have fallen apart.
So that's, and now comes, I thank you for your patience, maybe my first more interesting aspect.
It's part of this, that's the paradox of Protestantism, radically anthropocentric,
but at the same time let's look at ourselves with inhuman eyes.
Here I think, but I'm reading them, by them I mean assemblage theory, new materialism, object-oriented ontology, they can be combined with my position.
Because what's the true, let's call it naively, shattering ethical greatness, although I read it in a different way that it's usually read off.
I will focus here on so-called new materialism, Jane Bennett, this idea that we should look at our life in the middle of nature as an interaction of agents.
She calls them, I think, following Latour actants, and they interact and we should look at it through an inhuman gaze, to see this as a process of interaction, living interaction,
we are just one of the elements.
In her book, I think, Vibrant Matter, Jane Bennett provides a beautiful description of a trash site.
She said, we think trash side just nothing, piece of sheet there, things rotting.
But she says, what if we look at it with an imagined inhuman eye as a living process?
We have a complex interaction of rotting trash, worms, insects, abandoned machines, chemical poisons, and each place, each element, actant, plays its own never purely passive role.
I think, so-called new materialism or object-oriented ontology at its most radical, to provide this type of inhuman view.
And again, I think there is an authentic theoretical and ethico-political insight in such an approach.
Society thereby becomes a social phenomenon, but the limits of sociality are expanded to include all material bodies participating in the relevant assemblage.
Say, an ecological public is a group of bodies, some humans, most of them not, and they are subjected to harm defined as a diminished capacity for action.
Of course, the ethical implication is that we have to acknowledge the entanglement within a larger assemblage, like we are not, nature doesn't serve us, we are just one among the agents on the earth.
Here comes my first modest disagreement.
I think unknowingly this argument of her description also remains radically anthropocentric.
know in what sense, the more it tries to be objective at the level of content, the more it privileges us, human species, as the only species which has access to this universality.
That's my problem with those so-called deep ecologists who claim animals, even a Scandinavian friend of mine, wrote a book where he claims even beautiful canyons, pieces of nature,
should be treated as subject agents with human rights, like there is a beautiful organic totality in, he gives a beautiful example of wonderful rock formation in Iceland,
and he says not only, as it's popular to say now, animals should have their rights, not just human rights, priests should have their rights, even rivers should have their rights.
But you know what's the catch?
They don't know it.
We automatically, when we want to act as deep ecologists, is the most arrogant, anthropocentric position that you can imagine.
Because you automatically assume that we, yes, we apparently humiliate ourselves.
But we humans are the only agents who know, who have access to this universal dimension.
I mean, trees don't know about their rights.
When a river is ruining the trees, it doesn't know that it is infringing upon others' rights.
You know, it's the same falsity as the one, I think, of a certain type of multiculturalism where we claim that we are not the only ones who have the right.
Also, other cultures have the right.
But the more we humiliate ourselves of Western civilization, we are just one among them,
the more we act as the only one who has the access to the universal dimension and can say what the rights of the other such.
I felt this quite often in debates in the United States,
its typical arrogant, politically correct attitude, that, and once I witnessed it,
a white liberal guy, of course they're always white, defended black rights.
That's perfect, I'm radically for them.
But the problems were what that some black guys then didn't agree with him.
And basically he started to shout at him, like, you don't know what are your rights, I will tell you.
That's the hidden arrogance which, and I think it's the same problem with those who sympathize with refugees and so on and so on.
That's why I find suspicious
this eternal self-humiliation of Europeans.
I called it a reversed white man's burden.
You know, white man's burden is an old English expression, colonialist, for we white people are tasked by nature, God, whomever, our burden is to lead other nations to civilized life, whatever.
Now we have the opposite version of white man's burden, which is I think also a refined racism.
Whenever something happened in third world country, slaughter like Rwanda, it has to be an effect of colonialism.
And I have an African friend from Nigeria who got the point and exploded.
He said, you are such racist Europeans.
You don't even allow us to be genuinely evil.
You treat us as such innocent children that you know whenever we do something wrong, it must be your guilt.
This is the new version of white man's burden.
Let's look around.
There is a slaughter in Kampuchea.
Oh, it must be an effect of colonialism.
OK, let's go on.
Now things will get even much nastier.
I hear Jane Bennett, if she were to be here, would have exploded.
My ultimate example of assemblage would be not as a cheap provocation, not please don't misunderstand me, to read assemblage theory as proto-fascist, quite the opposite, that
I'm even tempted, but I'm afraid I would be even more attacked than I am, to write a short text on describing Auschwitz as an assemblage.
Let's forget about human suffering.
Let's look Auschwitz as a collaboration between humans, victims, worms, fire there and so on, a kind of objective process of material interaction.
And we can say not only the Nazis were agents, inmates were the agents, worms who ate the corpses if there were some, if they were not properly burned, were agents, and so on and so on.
And we can do it.
But now another philosophical point, I am so sad I don't have time to develop it.
What we get here, and now I will turn to Gilles Deleuze, towards whom I am critical but he is a genius, has ingenious insights, Deleuze said that his thinking tries to construct
a quote from Deleuze, a perception of reality as it was before or after man, humanity.
a perception released from its human coordinates.
He says we should view reality as quote iridescent chaos of a world before man.
Now I claim this doesn't mean cosmological speculation, how did big bang look.
It means that take a phenomenon like Auschwitz and look at it from outside of human concerns.
Of course, it's an, let's not misunderstand me, it's an utterly obscene vision.
Because in some sense, you cannot do it.
And here I come to my next point, I will be very brief, I really don't want to spend too much time.
I think that here Deleuze introduces, and he does it some, at some point he explicitly uses the terms.
the Kantian distinction between, for us, phenomenal reality and in itself, in the sense of nominal, independent of us,
not in this naive sense that in itself is reality out there the way it really is outside our view, but in itself as, I will put it like this, an impossible phenomenon.
The problem with the vision of Auschwitz that I gave to you.
It's not that, you cannot claim it's bluffing that it's the way Auschwitz really was.
And no, it's still our view, but it's impossible view.
It's too dramatic.
As ethical human being, we cannot afford to look at reality in that way.
Where inmates are, the burned people there are just reduced to one among the Aktans together with worms and whatever.
So my point is this one, that what, here Claude Lanzmann, with whom I often don't agree,
I think to shock you that he's, I find it very suspicious ethically, but at some point he was right.
He wrote somewhere that if he were to discover, let's say that some Nazis say this did it,
If he were to discover reels, I mean movie, cinema, with direct shooting of the most brutal
moments of Auschwitz, you see the bodies being gassed and how in panic mother climbs upon
her child to be a little bit higher, to be gassed, you know, the most brutal moments.
He said, I would burn it immediately.
And he is right.
you see too much there.
But you see the point.
It's not that you see objective reality the way it see.
You see a phenomenon, it's still a phenomenon, but a phenomenon which cannot be integrated into our reality.
Okay, that's philosophy.
Now I come to the final point, which may be problematic to some of you.
At some point I got even for showing this part in London, An old lady approached me and said, basically, she demanded from me a trigger warning.
She said, it was too brutal, you shouldn't have shown it to us.
But I don't believe in this logic of trigger warning, you know.
I think that academia is not a safe place when you, where you escape harsh life.
Academia on the contrary should confront you with brutality, you know.
Okay, so let's go on.
In this messy world where everything is on us as ethical subjects, but at the same time, you see the paradox I'm saying.
Look for example at slavery in the United States.
You can provide an objective history.
It was a collaboration of black stripes in Africa who were selling the slaves, blah blah.
You do an objective history.
you can do it, but it is an utter obscenity.
To do it from this neutral way, objectivity becomes an utter obscenity.
It is an obscenity to report on it in an objective way.
So again, if we try to bring together the two aspects, this rootless objectivity and at the same time utter ethical engagement, what kind of ethics do we get?
Here comes now my final example.
One of the good aspects of globalization, I think, I really love it, is I'm not against globalization, you know what, because it's genuinely multicultural.
By this I mean a simple thing, not multicultural in this usual left liberal sense, but in the sense that it's not only American culture and maybe French, English, also smaller nation get their chance.
Do you remember how years ago there was a period of South Korean, Taiwanese movies, there was a period even of Romanian movies, they are very good, wonderful sense of irony and so on.
Never forget that this is also a good effect of globalization.
It's not simply we will all eat hamburgers and watch Hollywood blockbusters.
If anything, My prediction is that one possible result of globalization will be that Hollywood will start losing.
I mean, who still wants to watch their stupid, these blockbusters where they even cannot produce new formulas and all they can do is endless remakes of old movies and then combining them.
Now you have Batman with Superman and so on, it's despair.
So what I am to say is that I like to read the good detective novels and they are, we
have now a new wave and that's what I like, I discovered.
It's no longer those, a couple of privileged sites, you know, like for classical Houdan in England, for hard-boiled novels, LA area or United States, maybe a little bit of France and so on.
Now they can happen, detective novels, literally everywhere at any time.
Do you know that you already have novels which take place in ancient Egypt?
A priest who is a detective at some stupid pharaoh's court.
You have detective novels, Stephen Saylor writes them, which happened in ancient Rome.
An acquaintance of Julius Caesar does the work.
You have one series on Alexander the Great and so on and so on anywhere, medieval, Umberto Eco started the first in medieval.
You have them now which take place in Tibet, in Russia, and my favorite are those which
take place in extreme circumstances, like you have now a whole subspecies of detective novels which take place in two of what at least in Europe we perceive as extreme moments.
the last years of war in Germany and the harshest Stalinism.
Like now, yesterday, I finished a novel called Jim McDermot, Pennamunde, where von Braun built rockets, Deceptions, where there is a murder in 1944, one of the engineers is shot in Pennamunde.
And I love, or you have Stalinist one, 35 bodies discovered in the middle of Moscow,
honest policeman tries to resolve the crisis but the victim is a foreigner, KGB intervenes, whole mess and okay not to get lost
along these lines okay I will tell you a dream because nobody will want to do it I don't care if you know it my simple dream is to do a novel but honest one not cynical which takes place
in Auschwitz like inmates and one is found strangled and they are all on the the edge of dying, but one of them tries to resolve it as a murder case.
And then I want to do a paradoxically upbeat tragic ending.
He solves the crime, but then they all go in a well-known, to a well-known place with a big burning machine and so on.
So along these lines, I love the new, this is old story, yesterday's news, Sweden even, even Iceland, Norway, Joe Nesbo.
My favorite are now, thrillers come from Denmark.
Not only novels, but also TV series, The Killing, and a series of novels which were made into films, a trilogy.
I want to show you a short clip from one of them.
The original title is flash and post, message in a bottle, and in English I don't know why, but it's a very good change of title.
It was changed into a conspiracy of fate.
Incidentally, I would love to write a text on the logic of, you know that now they no longer do it, but in the 50s and 60s, even later in some countries, they were always,
When they dubbed a movie for another country, they were changing the titles all the time.
For example, it's interesting, Hitchcock's North by Northwest.
In Germany, it was quite logically their Un siegtbare Drite, the invisible third, and so on.
My third example, sorry, I cannot abstain from playing bad taste racist jokes.
You know that for Brazilians, I spoke with you.
Portuguese are stupid.
The idea is all the intelligent guy from Portugal went to Brazil, idiots remained there.
So you know the story, I will not lose time, of Hitchcock's Psycho.
The joke in Brazil is that Psycho's title was changed in Portugal into the son who was his own mother, to make it understandable.
So along these lines, this time it works.
The title is A Conspiracy of Faith, a Danish mar from 2016, again, a call to illegal activity.
You can immediately download it from Pirate Bay or whatever.
I will not bore you with the story, but I will show you, just a minute, please, a four or five minute clip.
It's the story of an honest policeman who is described as a terminally depressive guy,
always in despair, of course totally 80s, and children are disappearing, they are killed in a strange, sadistic way,
and at the end he, the detective, locates the murderer, who is really a kind of ideal, passifal Aryan guy with blue long hair, a pathological murderer who thinks he's an instrument of devil, devil's son.
And his task is, he says, to destroy the faith of the parents.
It's not just to torture children, but he does this so that in presence of parents or so that parents are aware of it.
So he says his main task is not just to torture and kill people, but to do it in such a way that it destroys their faith.
And then some ethically quite shattering scene occurs.
I find it beautiful.
Don't be too alarmed.
If some of you trigger counterwarning,
are to be too shocked where a child is really drowned, killed.
It's not.
At the end of the film, he survived.
He was just unconscious so that you will not be too.
No, because some people at some talk, when I show this protested, how can you show this and so on and so on.
Don't be.
OK, let's show now, I think I described it enough.
Morissette, Moscow River.
Is it all show in there?
OK, stop.
I think even the movie now loses its spirit because it's nonetheless as if after this stance, you know, God intervenes from the outside.
But nonetheless, my point is a very simple one.
From my Christian atheist standpoint, no, the murderer is wrong.
God was there two times when he, the detective, offered himself, take me, take me, and when the girl didn't want to stab the guy.
So this is my crazy position.
I will try to be short not to go be short not to go too much on now.
Buy my next book where you will have all the chapter on this.
It's called Incontinence of the Void to appear MIT Press in October.
This is what I mean by Christian atheism.
Christ as a figure is not an active Redeemer.
It's just this impassive gaze which gives you the readiness to do it without any guarantee in faith.
I don't read this in this cheap way.
The guy, the detective, thinks he's an atheist, but really he's the deepest believer.
No, he is.
The murderer is right, the deepest believer.
You know, when the murderer tells him,
I never met a guy with such a faith as you.
But precisely because he needs no guarantee whatsoever in some higher force.
He just has to do it in a totally hopeless situation.
It's not that he wants to gain his place in heaven.
That's pure divine goodness.
You see a situation, you have to do it.
It's not because your account, oh, if I save this child,
I will be forgiven to cheat on my wife.
I will get a bed.
It has nothing to do with that.
So OK, why then, now you can ask me a simple question.
Why do I call this Christian atheism?
Why don't I simply say it's a materialist ethics?
Like this, pure goodness, no guarantees.
Here, of course, I am a materialist.
No misunderstanding here.
But my good friend, I really like him.
OK, not good friend.
I boast.
I exaggerate.
I met him two times.
We went along really well.
You know Rowan Williams, the leftist ex archbishop of Canterbury?
In his book of Dostoevsky, I don't like Dostoevsky, but I like his book Williams's of Dostoevsky.
He, among other things, I cannot restrain from briefly describing this to you, he provides the best reading that I can imagine of Dostoevsky's idiot.
You know, the usual reading of Idiot is, he's too divine for this world, a saint.
For Rowan Williams, it's a wonderful reading.
And it's so deeply true, if you know the story of Dostoevsky's Idiot.
He's not pure evil, Idiot, Prince Mishkin, but something much more refined.
There are people, and I met them, they really exist, who are really sincerely, no doubt, innocent good in themselves.
But the way they act in their social environment is that it's a kind of a wrong goodness.
They are absolutely sincerely good, but they cause catastrophe all around.
And for example, Prince Minsky, what does he cause?
Nastasia Filippona gets murdered by that other guy, or whatever, he causes catastrophe around himself.
Okay, the same Rowan Williams provided a wonderful definition in his book on Kostoevsky on what really is the divine dimension at its most elementary.
And he makes a reference to four British Catholic novelists – O'Connor, Percy, Spark and Ellis – and this is what he says about them.
All four create a world in which the secular majority account of what is going on is relativized.
But there is no simple alternative that anyone can step into by a single decision or even a series of decisions in the sense of this secular reality is shitty and there must be a higher order.
The religious dimension of this fiction lies in the insistent sense of incongruity, unmistakable even if no one within the fiction can say what we should be congruent with.
So it's just that our world is out of joint, inconsistent, lacking something, but it's literally negative theology, not negative theology in the usual sense, God is so much beyond that we cannot describe it properly, no, it's simply God is just this absence.
The empty place comes before what we fill it in through our images of God.
The basic divine dimension is this void, just this void, in the sense of our reality is something is terribly wrong with this reality.
And I think not only we can think weak,
we can think this in a materialist way, but the only proper way is to think in a materialist way.
And here things get complicated.
Here we should reject, you know, one of the most famous formula of Marx, that religion is the opium of the people.
First, be careful, Marx does not say for the people.
This would be way too vulgar for Marx.
It's not that, as in a certain naive form of enlightenment,
some evil priests are fabricating religion the way drug dealers like from Colombia, sorry, my bad, I'm so sorry, are fabricating.
No, it's of the people.
But you know what's my main argument against this formula today?
Yes, we have a religion which works as the opium of the people.
Of course, the terrorist fundamentalist religion, but never forget, not just in Muslim countries.
I'm here a radical pessimist.
You know that FBI has under observation in United States two million Christian fundamentalists suspected of being potentially terrorists.
I'm sorry to tell you that's basically the same percentage as among Arabs, you know.
So the question should not be just to be Islamophobic, it should be what is it in the dialectic of modern global capitalism that pushes people towards fundamentalism.
But OK, this is kind of also maybe a version today of the opium, religion as the opium of the people.
But there are at least two others, and I think Adorno already says this somewhere.
We have two other opiums of the people.
You will guess, I hope, which are they.
Opium and people.
For populists, their opium is people themselves.
You know this phantasmatic image, people, and so on.
Marine Le Pen's opium are the people, and so on.
The true French people threatened by.
And the other opium of the people is opium.
For many intellectuals, opium is drugs.
It's opium, as you know.
So the way to get out of it, I am for a religious dimension, but in this purely abstract way,
and I don't have time to do it, a wonderful reading can be given in this sense to link, since these guys are Danish people, to link with the obvious person, with Kierkegaard,
whose formulas of religion, when he says God is not something we relate to, God is relating itself, and all those formulas who at least I think come to the edge of a certain type of very paradoxical materialism.
I don't want to bore you too much, and I hope you will not protest again against this politically correct madness I've shown you too much.
My God, if you, I, you know, also when I talk about rapes, people claim you shouldn't talk in such plastic terms or whatever, you know, that it's shocking.
Fuck you, it should be shocking, you know, because if you just abstractly describe it,
then it doesn't really affect you, then it's just, oh, it's like bureaucratic statistics, you know.
No, you should be shocked by the horrors which go on.
Thanks very much for your kind patience.
我想说的是 我认为我所谓的基督教无神论仍然是符合当今困境的伦理立场
好吧 让我从一个简单的观察开始
那些追随晦涩的精神宇宙论推测的人肯定听说过这个领域最流行的话题之一
这些神话故事 当三个行星 通常是地球、月球和太阳 找到自己沿着同一轴线时
那么一些大的灾难性事件就会发生 整个宇宙秩序会瞬间被打乱 宇宙必须找到新的平衡
你们记得么 之前的玛雅人的古老语言 虽然它并没有被当真
但在2012年也引起了一些恐慌 因为他们认为是地球、月球和太阳处于同一条线上是不好的事情
我认为 从政治上讲 今年 2017年 这种情况同样适用 这是一个三重纪念日
2017年 我们不仅仅庆祝十月革命百年纪念 1917年
还有马克思《资本论》第一版发行150周年纪念 1867年 也许是最悲剧的事件
所谓的SH公社50周年纪念 当时是东印度伟大的无产阶级Cultural Revolution的高潮时刻
这是一个奇妙的时刻 也许是20世纪共产主义的关键时刻
SH的居民 工人和学生
决定把Mao的号召当真 你知道当Mao说攻打司令部时
你既不需要party也不需要军队
而应该由人民接管
好吧 他们把这当真了 简单直接地推翻了办公室 摧毁了当地communist party的办公室 无视了军队 并接管了
这是一个关键点 因为然后Mao不得不派军队
这是一个极其悲惨的事件 因为当时人们不知道 这（会）是Cultural Revolution中最大的一场战斗
忽略之前那些--虽然它们也是悲剧性的--所有那些事情（小打小闹） 你知道 red guard discs拔须 恐吓教授、知识分子 所有那些
SH的那场战斗（不是这样） 当军队转而对抗真正的革命者
人们无法知道准确的统计报告 死者是数万还是数十万
但我认为这个事件很吸引人 因为我不喜欢这个大问题 Mao是否真诚？
在某种程度上 他不是
很明显 他引发Cultural Revolution是为了在国家中重新获得他的全部权力
但Mao是否在操纵并不重要
事情失控了
普通工人把它当回事了
我们直接让社会来统治
我们不需要党 我们不需要军队等等 它走得太远了
所以我认为这三个事件标志着共产主义运动的三个阶段
首先 马克思的《资本论》概述了共产主义革命的理论基础
然后 十月革命是第一次成功的尝试 推翻资产阶级国家并建立新的社会经济秩序
接着 SH公社代表了立即实现共产主义愿景最大胆方面的最激进尝试
废除国家权力 实施直接人民权力 以地方社区网络的形式组织
它没有成功 当然 我今天不会回答那个大问题 即出了什么问题？
我认为 这就是我的假设 这个周期出了什么问题？
也许答案是有待解决的 人们不会谈论它 但至少对我来说 作为一名基督徒 这是关键日期
难道你不知道今天我们还有另一个--我们有四个行星排成一线--又一个重大纪念日
2017年是1517年500周年纪念 当时马丁·路德在那扇门上贴出了新教的95条论纲
我仍然认为新教是你能想象的最关键的宗教事件
为什么？
让我从一个非常简化的方式开始
但我并不是完全在吹牛 因为我在剑桥的一个神学研讨会上展示了这篇文章的一个版本 它进行得很顺利
我还能说什么呢？
所以我并不是完全在吹牛
我并不是完全在吹牛
让我从东正教、天主教和新教的三重体开始讲起
我认为 也许我错了
东正教传统的核心是神化的概念 人变得像上帝一样
或引用亚历山大的圣亚他那修的话 引号
她 基督或上帝 成为肉身（具体化） 以便我们可以成为上帝 引号结束
这可能看似荒谬
堕落有罪的人可以通过耶稣这位神的化身 变得像上帝一样圣洁
然后圣马克西穆斯修士以相同的方式写道 再次引用
上帝道成肉身为我们带来了以希望看待人性神化的确凿保证
这使得人能够在同样的程度上成为神 正如上帝自己成为了人
让我们成为全能神的形象
内在不带任何尘世之物
以便我们能与神为伍并成为神
从神那里接受我们作为神的存在 引号结束
这个东正教公式 上帝成为人 是为了人可以成为上帝
我认为 这是新教彻底拒绝的
新教最深刻的洞见 虽然它已经隐含在圣经中 是非常简单地说
上帝成为人 就这样 没有更多
一切已经在化身中发生了
需要添加的只是一个视角的转变
我认为在真正的基督教视野中 没有所谓的复活
圣灵（本身）已经是复活
复活发生在基督教社区中
上帝死了 他仍然是死亡的
我们被宣判去获得自由
圣灵社会不是--我在这里读到--基督教采用了一种彻底的无神论方式
圣灵不是某种综合体
（圣灵不是）上帝 人 然后它们被汇集在一起
不 通过十字架上的钉死 正是那种类型的神 那种原始的观念...
在天上 有一个伟大的老人 有着长长的胡须 他照顾着我们 所以不用太担心
最终 我们会被照顾的
黑格尔--我最喜欢的--表达得很好
他说 在十字架上死去的不是上帝的地上代表
而是上帝本身 那个超越的上帝
那么余留的是什么
我们在我们的自由中
这才是真正的基督教“诡计”
我说 上帝给了我们所有的自由
他说 但上帝没有
上帝放弃了 他只是创造了世界 而后留我们独自一人 上帝抛弃了我们
我会说 但那是自由的另一个名字
你应该换个角度
或者用另一种方式说 我在这里 我是基于我所爱的切斯特顿开始的一些非常好的神学阅读
在其他宗教中 简单来说 人
人是从上帝那里堕落而来到尘世
所以（它们的）想法是 让我们通过一些愚蠢的精神练习--无论是什么--爬回去
比如 让我们摆脱我们的罪恶本性 回到上帝那里
但基督教的解决方案是一个完全不同的选择 举例来说
假设你作为一个普通信徒 发现自己被上帝完全抛弃了
那么出路是什么 不是说 让我通过做一些好事或自我惩罚来变得纯洁 不 就是在那个时候 当我被上帝完全抛弃时
我（才开始能够）认同基督 他发现自己处于完全相同的位置 带着那句著名的话 父亲 父亲 你为什么离弃我
所以这是一个奇妙的洞察 你应该以一种非常黑格尔的方式看到 我们如何克服与上帝的分离 不是通过重新加入上帝 而是意识到这种分离也是上帝自身的分离
在那一点上 我们是神圣的
因为再次 神性的终极时刻是那一刻 正如吉尔伯特·基思·切斯特顿所说 上帝自己变成无神论者的那一刻
记住 在十字架上 当基督说 父亲 父亲 你为什么离弃我时 他短暂成为一个非信徒
这是一个疯狂的时刻
你在其他宗教中找不到这个
在其他宗教中 你确实找到了背弃上帝的人
但你在（那个宗教里能）找到上帝背弃了自己呢？
而且 基督教的解决方案不是 你受苦 你低下 但别担心 （而后会）有好消息
不 没有好消息
好消息只是对坏消息的不同视角转变
我们仍然被上帝抛弃
上帝不会来拯救我们
正如那些不愚蠢的保守神学家所知 比如我最喜欢的法国保守天主教徒保罗·克洛岱尔 他非常漂亮地说 基督教的终极秘密不是信任上帝
（像是说）情况可能看起来糟糕 但上帝会帮助你
不 正好相反
上帝需要我们的帮助
只有我们能拯救上帝
换句话说 神性的 还有一些神智的推测--我就不深究了 我们没有时间浪费在这里--
它们以一种奇妙的方式发展这一点 他们声称转世的秘密不是上帝做了一些英雄般的事来赎回我们
上帝 没有道成肉身的上帝不是完全的上帝
上帝通过化身成人来成为完全的上帝
这是我最喜欢的一个解决方案之一 除了黑格尔 德国唯心主义者谢林
--海德格尔后来在他的基础上发展了这一点--这两篇文本 尤其是《自由论》
谢林关于人类自由本质的文本
以及后来关于世界时代的《世界纪》片段
他展开了这个观点 上帝如何产生逻各斯 生下了逻各斯的儿子--谢林在字面意思上这样说--为了把自己从自己的疯狂中拯救出来
如果我可以愤世嫉俗一点 你知道 精神病医生说 如果你陷入精神病 你需要创造性治疗 你知道 通过工作
嗯 那就是上帝所做的
还有一些 如果你认为我在吹牛
一些非常聪明的新教神学家得出了相同的结论
比如 我的一位挪威朋友给了我一个参考 并且因为这不是一本众所周知的书 只在挪威出名 他给我翻译了一些部分
那个人的名字是彼得·韦塞尔·扎克韦 一本关于新教上帝的书
这是对约伯记的阅读
你知道他的解读是什么吗？
约伯在遇到上帝时发现了什么 当他意识到上帝正在做一些非常奇怪的事情 正在无缘无故地惩罚他？
这里是扎普费尔的一段引用 约伯发现自己面对一个世界统治者 上帝 具有怪诞的原始性
一个宇宙洞穴居住者 一个吹牛和大放厥词的人 几乎在他对精神文化的完全无知中令人愉快
对约伯来说新的不是上帝在量化术语中的伟大 那我们事先完全知道
新的是上帝在定性上的卑微
我认为这也是新教大主题——预定论的深刻洞察
它的意思是 上帝只是和我们玩一个残酷的游戏 他不在乎
上帝预先决定了 你得救了 你迷失了 完全不考虑我们在做什么
我认为这是正确的路线
我认为 正如聪明的新教徒所看到的 那种天主教的方式 将我们的救赎与我们的善行联系起来 立即引入了一种可操作的因素 一种金融交易
我看到那个孩子正在溺水 我应该救还是不救 好吧 我可能会因此得救 所以去他的 为什么不做呢？
这使我们的善行成为一种几乎可以说是对未来的金融投资的一部分
但正如路德非常聪明地指出的 如果存在预定论 那么它的解决方案就是纯粹的善行
因为你看到一个孩子在溺水 抱歉用这个可怜的例子 你非常清楚 无论你救不救那个孩子 都对你的救赎没有任何帮助
所以 唯有善良才促使你去做这件事
所以让我们继续这里
在这种情况下 即解决办法不是神与人的某种重新统一
我们通过一个简单的认识来克服我们对上帝的异化 那就是上帝已经从自己那里异化 自我放弃了
我喜欢在这里应用黑格尔对古希腊雕像的精彩解读 那对我们是不可理解的 比如斯芬克斯意味着什么？
你知道黑格尔的公式是什么
古希腊人的秘密 对我们来说是秘密 对古希腊人自己也是秘密
黑格尔的神学正是这个 神性的秘密也是对神性本身的秘密
这是古老的神秘主题
黑格尔也谈到了这一点
你在迈斯特·埃克哈特和所有其他人那里找到它 把历史带入上帝自身
我们在地球上发生的事 我们的神学活动 某种方式决定了上帝自身的命运
（所以）情况正好相反
不是上帝决定（一切） 不
在我们的斗争中 我们为上帝自身的命运而战
那么如何提出--现在可能会有点困难--适当的神学观点
我认为我在我的课堂上已经对此进行了一些即兴发挥
这是否意味着新教简单地废除了我们的自由？
每个了解路德的人 我没有时间深入讨论 但我已经写好了
对马丁·路德与托马斯·闵采尔之间的紧张关系进行了详细分析 后者是德国农民起义的伟大神学家
也许这会让你感到惊讶 但我几乎更支持早期的路德
他是正确的 闵采尔在批评路德支持权威们 等等 是正确的
但我认为闵采尔 已经太接近了
接近于这种倾向于极权主义的扭曲工具化立场
因为路德是正确的 这是他最伟大的神学洞察 坚持神的不可入性
这写成唯物主义方式 并不意味着上帝知道他在做什么 我们只是无法渗透（了解）它
这意味着引用自Sapwe 上帝是疯狂的 无法了解
所以路德正是警告我们所谓的今天的原教旨主义
任何一个历史上的施动者的立场--喔 我的天 这里发生了什么？
我有点迷信了 昨天这里还只有一只 好吧 至少它们不是黑猫 我们会幸存的
这就是Mao派运动 一分为二--
好吧 抱歉 让我们继续 路德很接近这一点了 这是路德直接禁止的 即将自己的政治运动视为神圣意志的直接工具
他坚持这种彻底的不可渗透性 即 存在着宿命 但我们永远不知道宿命是什么
就像我们的生活是被提前决定的 但我们永远无法知道
所以绝对禁止声称“我是神圣意志的工具” 就像斯大林主义共产主义者以不同方式阐述 “历史的必然性通过我向共产主义前进”
不 我们不能这样做
我认为这是真正的自由
这种思想 我的生活是预定的 但我不知道是什么
需要通过可怕的斗争去做出正确的决定
因为你知道 这里常识不起作用
因为常识会告诉我们 你为什么担心？
如果有宿命论 坐下来手淫 看色情电影 没关系
不 这个想法也是--这就是为什么它不起作用 它解释了 我们都知道 我甚至在重复自己 我想几年前 我已经在这里讲过了 很抱歉--
因为这也解释了宿命论和自由的这个悖论 解释了这个马克斯·韦伯的经典文章的最大谜团 为什么新教 这个基于宿命论的宗教
成为了资本主义的宗教背景 至少最初如此 （因为）它正是最活跃的社会系统 一个时刻都要求你活跃如狂的系统
再说 如果一切都是预定的 那逻辑上不是应该说 去他的 我躺下来 等上帝来的时候叫醒我 先让我一个人呆着吧
韦伯清楚地看到了这一点 路德也是 正因为你知道你的命运是预定的 但不知道你的命运是什么 所以着推动你进行不停的活动
我认为这个决定 这个困难的决定去发现是否存在宿命 （是否存在）信仰的必然性
信仰是什么 是更接近真正的自由--我用过一个隐喻 如果你是我之前课堂的学生的话 很抱歉--
那种简单的自由 我去糕点店 他们有草莓蛋糕、巧克力蛋糕、香草蛋糕 或者我将选择哪一个 你知道 这种简单的选择自由
不 真正的自由是这样的 即使现在你会说我疯了
但让我给你一个我在之前课上举出过的例子
想想爱情 对于爱情中另一客体的选择
它必须是自由的 否则 它就不是爱 对吗？
但它从未作为一个所谓的自由选择而发生在你身上
如果你说 哦 现在我将爱上那个女士/男士 那是假的
这是一个自由的决定 但正如谢林所说 一个超越的 先于时间的自由决定 而你恰恰以其相反的、作为你的命运的方式体验它
你体验爱情如同 我的天 我无法逃脱 我被困在其中
那才是真正的自由
那是根本的自由
现在你会说 这是感性的猜测
不 我会用我课上的另一个例子
难道这和艰难的政治决定不一样吗？
不是那些简单的决定 投票给马克龙 还是投票给勒庞 我不在乎
但让我们来一个可怜的例子
发生了战争 我的国家被攻击 我必须决定我是否冒着生命危险去做
这是我做出的自由决定
但如果你做出了艰难的决定 你将要战斗 你不会将其视为一种选择
你感受到的是 我真希望不去做 但这是我的责任 我不得不做
我必须去做
我认为这提供了这种奇妙的辩证法 据我所知 只有黑格尔在哲学中清晰地描述过
只有黑格尔清晰地描述了如果我们以唯物主义方式去解读新教的宿命论
它要比简单的观念——有宿命论 一切都是决定的——更具有悖论性
意味着我们有一个命运 但我们反过来创造这个命运
比如 我自由地决定了某件事情 一旦我做出决定 从事后来看 它就是必然的
如果我做了正确的事情 我会感受到 我的天啊 我别无选择 我必须这么做
这就是自由
所以 这是我对新教的第一个观点
这意味着 你不仅自由 而且你比你所认为的更自由
你甚至对你的命运、你的必然性负责
再次 正如我已经在我的课上解释的 精神分析学在这里与新教相遇
因为在精神分析中 一个明显的结论是 某种形式的宿命论
你知道 就像 我认为我是一个自由的存在 但并不 一切都被我的过去的创伤--无论什么--预先决定了 所以我发现我并不自由
这是半个世纪前法国结构主义盛行时的流行教训
这就是精神分析学被理解的方式 结构主义精神分析学
你认为你是一个自由的主体 不 你只是一个傀儡 大他者、象征秩序在操控你 等等
但是看 拉康在这里跟随弗洛伊德 是的 你是被过度决定的 但你不能使用这种过度决定或心理必然性作为借口
你知道 像是 用粗俗的话说 很抱歉
我强奸了一个孩子 然后我对法官说 对不起 伙计们 我能怎么办？
我是被我的无意识复杂性过度决定的
不 虽然你是被命运预定的 但你甚至对那也负有责任
你负有更根本的责任
我现在不能深入讨论 我已经在我的课上讨论了同样的问题也适用于康德伦理学 这就是为什么它是一件伟大的事情
康德说 先做康德 然后做灵魂
你能做到 因为你必须做到
你没有借口不去履行你的职责
如果那是你的职责 你必须去做
但是康德--这并不经常被注意到 甚至更进一步--
他还暗示 即使“履行你的职责”也不能成为履行你职责的借口
比如克里斯 我恨你 让我做一些事
我必须做一些事 那是我的职责去伤害你
（但其实）我没有权力告诉你 对不起 伙计 但这是我的职责
不 我没有权力将其外化
我不仅仅是负有履行我的职责的责任
我还必须在主观上完全认同我的职责 以理解我的职责是什么
这就是为什么 顺便说一句 我在我的课上简要提到了这一点 现在我将停止抄袭我自己
别担心 我不会重复我的课程
这就是为什么我认为 尽管我佩服她 在她那本其他方面精彩的《耶路撒冷的艾希曼》中
如果我记得正确的话 汉娜·阿伦特错了
当她认真对待艾希曼的说法 他只是一个标准的康德主义者
他为他自己履行了职责 职责体现在元首的命令中 所以对不起 我在履行我的职责
不 艾希曼确切地做了错误的事情
他不是一个康德主义者 因为他做了康德严格禁止的事情
他把职责用作借口 对不起 我杀害了数百万犹太人 我能怎么办 那是我的职责
不 你不能将你的职责视为某种你只需遵循的客观决定
你对你的职责负有根本的责任
现在我要让问题复杂化
现在结束自我推销
你会得到一些新内容
这个解决方案 这种必要性与自由的辩证相互联系 在这里 是的 存在必要性
但这种必要性 在更深层次上 是偶然的
就像 你以一种偶然的方式做某事
一旦你做了 它事后成为你的命运
这个解决方案只在一个条件下有效
（即）主体、信徒、施动者 完全受到他或她有限主观性视野的约束（的时候）
新教禁止的是这种想法 即作为一个信徒 我可以 可以说
站在自己之外、之上的位置 将自己视为浩瀚现实中的一个微小粒子
既然我已经提到了Mao 我想在哲学层面上批评他一下
顺便说一下 因为我像这样的一些观点 阿伦·巴迪欧甚至现在对我很生气 你知道的
我认为Mao在他部署他的“奥林匹克视野”时犯了错误 将人类的经历简化为一个微不足道的宇宙细节
你知道 在他那句著名的话中 他说 “我们不怕原子战争” 好吧 原则上我同意
但Mao接着说了这样一句话 引用Mao的话 美国用它那一小堆原子弹是无法消灭东印度民族的
即使美国的原子弹如此强大 当它们投放在东印度时 能够穿透地球 甚至将地球炸毁 这对整个宇宙来说几乎意味着什么都没有
尽管这对太阳系来说可能是一个重大事件
你知道 这有点奇怪的借口
好吧 美国人可以摧毁我们 但从宇宙的角度来看 这意味着什么呢？
我认为这个论点 Mao的论点 只有在一种伪康德方式下才行得通
问题是 Mao是从哪个主观位置发表这个声明的？
他行为就像他是从一个完全外部的、纯粹神圣的位置发言 从那里你可以客观地看到人类的现实 然后你可以说
好吧 我们的地球被炸毁了 去他的 一个小星球上的小光点 谁在乎？
但这里我没有时间发展它 但这是美妙的神学话题
聪明的新教有一个奇妙的视角 那就是偶然性和必然性之间的连接再次被提及
一方面 是的 我们是浩瀚宇宙中的微小部分
新教不是种族中心主义的 这就是为什么新教在某种程度上代表了现代性 正是现代科学的宗教背景 正是引入了现实的客观观点
你知道 在新教之前 中世纪的世界是以地球为中心
尽管我们人类不是宇宙的中心 上帝是 但尽管如此 我们是被创造的宇宙的最高点 一切都围绕我们转动
所以 新教的统一之处 我现在没有时间去发展它 只是为了给出一个想法 我认为这是一些奇妙的东西
同时 这种极其残酷的观点
从一个非人类的视角看 我们什么都不是
地球上的一个微小物种 不重要
但尽管如此 由于我们在道德实践中永远无法真正假设这种观点 即这种外部视角
（那么）我们必须行动 就好像不管何时--康德把这个说得很好--尽管客观科学告诉我们 去他的 我们是宇宙中的一粒尘埃
尽管如此 在一场巨大的道德斗争中 决定的不仅仅是我们的命运 可以说--康德说的很好--整个宇宙都是作为我们这场斗争的背景而创造的
你知道 我喜欢这种极端的种族中心主义的统一
世界被创造出来 以便我们可以进行这场战斗 以及这种极端的外部观点
因为这在某种程度上是 当你见证一个大的变革 革命或任何事情
甚至在大屠杀中 我认为智慧的论点 即使是哈贝马斯也提出了 他试图成为一个理性主义者
但哈贝马斯 我不同意他的观点 曾经提出了一个很好的观点 他说大屠杀 我还会补充说 像刚果发生的以及其他可怕的事情等等
发生了如此可怕的事情 当你将其简化为一个简单的人类事件时 你以某种方式减少了其恐怖性
在阶级斗争中出了问题 无论什么 说大屠杀只是阶级斗争和努力的一个小分支是可怕的
哈贝马斯非常智慧地说 神学维度在这里只是一种方式 一种特定的方式 来标志发生了如此可怕的事情 它不适合我们的宇宙
我们不能 我会这样说 我们不能简单地将其重新归类为另一个历史事件
这就是为什么 不知道这是不是一本关于大屠杀的书的标题 你可能纠正我 也许你更了解 《黑太阳》 太阳本身变黑了 你知道 就像有人很好地说 当像大屠杀这样的事情发生时 世界还能继续存在 这是一种耻辱
如果世界上有基本的道德 出于羞耻 世界应该崩溃
所以这就是 现在来了 我感谢你的耐心 也许是我第一个更有趣的观点
这是新教的悖论的一部分 彻底的人类中心主义
但同时让我们用非人类的眼光看待自己
在这里 我认为 但我在解读他们 我指的是组合论、新唯物主义、面向对象的本体论 它们可以和我的立场结合起来
因为什么是真正的--让我们天真地称之为--震撼性的伦理伟大 尽管我以一种少见的方式解读它
我将在这里专注于所谓的新唯物主义 简·班尼特 即 我们应该将我们的生活视为自然中各种施动者之间的相互作用
她称它们为施动者 我认为是跟随拉图尔的 它们相互作用 我们应该通过一个非人类的视角来看待它 将其视为一个生活的相互作用过程
我们只是其中的一个元素
在她的书中 我认为是《活力物质》 简·班尼特提供了一个垃圾场的美丽描述
她说 我们认为垃圾场里什么都没有 那里有一堆垃圾在腐烂
但她说 如果我们用一个想象中的非人类眼光看待它 作为一个生活过程怎么样？
我们有一个复杂的腐烂垃圾、蠕虫、昆虫、被遗弃的机器、化学毒素的相互作用 每个地方、每个元素、施动者 都扮演着它自己从不完全被动的角色
我认为 所谓的新唯物主义或面向对象的本体论在其最激进的形式上 提供了这种非人类视角
再次 我认为这种方法中有一个真正的理论和伦理政治洞察
因此 社会成为一个社会现象 但社会性的界限被扩展到包括所有参与相关集合的物质实体
比如 一个公共生态是一群实体 一些是人类 大多数不是 他们受到的伤害被定义为行动能力下降
当然 伦理含义是 我们必须承认在更大的组合体中的纠缠--比如我们不是--自然不是为我们服务的 我们只是地球上众多施动者中的一个
这是我的第一个小小的分歧
我认为不知不觉中 她的描述也仍然是彻底的人类中心主义
知道是什么意思吗 越是试图在内容层面上保持客观 就越是将我们、人类物种进行特殊化 即作为唯一能够接触到这种普遍性的物种
这是我对那些所谓的深层生态学家的问题 他们声称动物--甚至我的一个斯堪的纳维亚朋友写了一本书 他声称甚至美丽的峡谷、自然的一部分
应该被视为拥有人权的主体施动者 就像有一个美丽的有机整体 在他给出的冰岛的一个美丽岩石形成的例子中
他说 不仅如现在流行的说法 即动物应该拥有它们的权利 不仅是人类权利 （而且）森林应该拥有他们的权利 甚至河流也应该有它们的权利
但你知道问题在哪里吗？
它们不知道
当我们想要充当深层生态学家时 我们自然而然地就会采取你能想象到的最傲慢、以人类为中心的立场
因为你自动假设我们--是的 我们表面上贬低了自己--
但我们人类是唯一了解、拥有通往这个普遍维度通道的施动者
我的意思是 树木不知道它们的权利
当一条河流在破坏树木时 它不知道它正在侵犯其他人的权利
你知道 这和某种类型的多元文化主义的虚假性是一样的 我们声称我们不是唯一拥有权利的人
其他文化也有权利
但我们越是自贬我们的西方文明--我们只是其中之一--
我们越是行为得就像我们是唯一能够接触到普遍维度并且可以说出其他人的权利是什么的人
我在美国的辩论中经常感到这一点
它是典型的傲慢的 政治上正确的态度 一旦我见证了这样的情况
一个白人自由主义者 当然他们总是白人 为黑人权利辩护
这很完美 我彻底支持他们
但问题是 而后 一些黑人不同意他
基本上他（白人）就开始对他们大喊 就像 你不知道你的权利是什么 我会告诉你
这是隐藏的傲慢 我认为这与那些同情难民的人有同样的问题
这就是为什么我对这种永恒的欧洲人自我羞辱感到怀疑
这是我所说的白人负担的逆转
你知道 白人负担是一个古老的英语表达 殖民主义者 我们白人被自然、上帝、或任何人赋予任务 我们的负担是引领其他国家走向文明生活 等等
现在我们有了白人负担的相反版本 我认为这也是一种精致的种族主义
每当第三世界国家发生一些事情 比如卢旺达的屠杀 （那么）它必须是殖民主义的影响
我有一个来自尼日利亚的非洲朋友 他明白了这一点 他爆发了
他说 你们这些欧洲人真是种族主义者
你们甚至不允许我们真正地邪恶
你们把我们当成如此天真的孩子 你们认为 每当我们做错事 它一定是你们的过错
这是白人负担的新版本
让我们环顾四周
柬埔寨发生了大屠杀
哦 它一定是殖民主义的影响
好吧 我们继续
现在事情会变得更加糟糕
我认为简·班尼特 如果她在这里 她会爆炸的
我有关组合论的最后一个例子不是一种廉价的挑衅 请不要误解我 将组合理论解读为原始法西斯主义 恰恰相反
我甚至很想--但我害怕我会受到更多的攻击--写一篇简短的文章来描述奥斯威辛作为一个组合体以让我们忘记人类的苦难
让我们将奥斯威辛视为人类、受害者、蠕虫、火焰等的合作 一种物质相互作用的客观过程
我们可以说不仅是纳粹是施动者 犯人是施动者 吃尸体的蠕虫（如果有的话 如果它们没有被完全烧毁）是施动者 等等
我们可以这样做
但现在另一个哲学观点 我很遗憾我没有时间来展开它
我们在这里得到的 现在我将转向吉尔·德勒兹 我对他持批评态度 但他是一个天才 拥有独到的见解 德勒兹说他的思想试图构建--
引用 一种视角 将现实视为在人类之前或之后的样子
一种从人类坐标中释放出来的感知
他说我们应该将现实视为引用“人类之前的世界的五彩缤纷的混沌”
现在我声称这并不意味着宇宙学的推测 比如大爆炸看起来如何
它意味着拿一个现象 比如奥斯威辛 从人类关切之外来看待它
当然 这是一个极端亵渎的视角
因为在某种意义上 你做不到这一点
这里我来到我的下一个观点 我将非常简短 我真的不想花太多时间
我认为 在这里德勒兹引入了康德之间的区分 他在某些时候明确使用了这些术语
区分了对我们而言的现象实在和自身之中的实在 以名义上、独立于我们的意义上
而不是以一种天真的方式认为 自身之中的实在就是外在于我们视角之外的实际存在的现实 而是将其视为--我将这样表达--一个不可能的现象
我给你们的奥斯威辛的视角的问题
不是说 你不能声称这是虚张声势 那是奥斯威辛真实的样子
不 它仍然是我们的视角 但它是不可能的视角
这太戏剧化了
作为道德的人 我们无法承受以那种方式看待现实
囚犯们 被烧毁的人仅仅被简化为一个行动体 与蠕虫等一道
所以我的观点是 这里的克洛德·兰茨曼 我经常不同意他
我认为他是在惊吓你们 我发现他在道德上非常可疑 但在某些时刻他是正确的
他写道如果他发现 比方说一些纳粹这样做了
如果他发现了胶卷 我的意思是电影 有直接拍摄的奥斯威辛最残酷的时刻
你看到肉体被毒气杀死 以及在恐慌中的母亲如何爬到她的孩子上面
（踩着孩子）以使自己站得更高 （离毒气远一点）以求生 你知道 最残酷的时刻
他说 我会立即烧掉它
他是对的
你在这里看到得太多了
但这里的要点是
这不是说你看到了客观现实的方式
你看到了一个现象 它仍然是一个现象 但是这是一个无法被整合进我们的现实的现象
好的 这是哲学
现在我来到最后一点 这可能对你们中的一些人来说是有问题的
在某个时候 我甚至因为在伦敦展示这一部分而受到批评 一位老太太走近我 基本上是要求我给出一个触发警告
她说 这太残酷了 你不应该向我们展示它
但我不相信触发警告的逻辑 你知道
我认为学术不是一个安全的地方--在那里你逃避艰苦的生活--
相反 学术应该让你面对残酷 你知道
好的 所以让我们继续
在这个混乱的世界里 一切都取决于我们作为道德主体 但同时 你看到我所说的悖论
例如 看看美国的奴隶制
你可以提供一个客观的历史
这是非洲黑人部落合作出售奴隶 等等
你做一个客观的历史
你可以这样做 但这是一种绝对的亵渎
以这种中立的方式做 客观性变成了完全的亵渎
以客观的方式报告它是一种亵渎
所以再次 如果我们试图将这两个方面结合起来 即这种无根的客观性 同时又完全的道德参与 我们会得到什么样的道德呢
现在来到我的最后一个例子
全球化的好方面之一 我认为 我真的喜欢它 我不反对全球化 你知道为什么吗 因为它是真正的多元文化
我的意思是 不是以这种通常的左翼自由主义意义上的多元文化 而是意味着不仅仅是美国文化 也许法国、英国 小国家也有机会
你还记得多年前有一段时间的韩国、Taiwanese电影 甚至一段时间的罗马尼亚电影 他们非常好 有奇妙的讽刺意味等等
永远不要忘记 这也是全球化的好效果
不是简单地说 我们都将吃汉堡包和观看好莱坞大片
如果有什么 我的预测是全球化的一个可能结果将是好莱坞会开始失去地位
我的意思是 谁还想看他们那些愚蠢的大片 他们甚至不能制作新的公式 他们所能做的就是无休止地翻拍旧电影 然后将它们结合起来
现在你有蝙蝠侠与超人等等 真是绝望
所以我想说的是 我喜欢阅读好的侦探小说
而且我们现在有一个新的浪潮 这是我喜欢的 我发现了
不再是那些 几个特权地点 你知道 就像英格兰的经典侦探小说 美国洛杉矶地区的硬汉侦探小说 或许还有法国的一些作品等等
现在侦探小说可以发生在任何地方 任何时间
你知道吗 你已经有小说发生在古埃及？
一位牧师是某个愚蠢法老宫廷的侦探
你有侦探小说 斯蒂芬·塞勒写的 发生在古罗马
一位与朱利叶斯·凯撒熟识的人做了这项工作
你有关于亚历山大大帝的系列 等等任何地方 中世纪 翁贝托·艾柯首先在中世纪开始了
现在有些小说发生在西藏、俄罗斯 我最喜欢的是那些发生在极端环境中的小说
比如现在有一整个侦探小说的子类别 发生在我们至少在欧洲视为极端时刻的两个时期
德国战争的最后几年和最严酷的斯大林主义
比如 昨天 我刚读完一本叫做吉姆·麦克德莫特的《佩纳蒙德》 讲的是冯·布劳恩建造火箭的地方 1944年佩纳蒙德发生了一场谋杀 一名工程师被枪杀
我喜欢--或者你有斯大林主义--莫斯科市中心发现了35具尸体
一名正直的警察试图解决危机 但受害者是外国人 克格勃介入 一团糟 好吧 为了不迷失方向
沿着这些线索好吧 我会告诉你一个梦想 因为没人会想做这个 我不在乎你知不知道 我的简单梦想是写一部小说 但是诚实的 不是讽刺的
发生在奥斯威辛 囚犯之一被发现被勒死 他们都在死亡边缘 但其中一个人试图把它当作谋杀案来解决
然后我想做一个悲剧性的乐观结局
他解决了谋杀案 但然后他们都走向一个众所周知的地方 有一个大型的焚烧设备等等
沿着这些线索 我喜欢新的 这是老掉牙的新闻 甚至是瑞典 甚至是冰岛 挪威 乔·内斯博
我最喜欢的现在是 来自丹麦的惊悚小说
不仅是小说 还有电视剧 《杀戮》和一系列被改编成电影的小说 一个三部曲
我想给你们放一个短片段 来自其中之一
原标题是《闪光和邮件--信息在瓶子里》--在英语中我不知道为什么 但这是一个很好的标题变化--
它被改成了《命运的阴谋》
顺便说一下 我很想写一篇关于逻辑的文章 你知道 现在他们不再这样做了 但在50年代和60年代 甚至在一些国家晚些时候 他们总是--
当他们为另一个国家配音一部电影时--他们总是在改变标题
例如 这很有趣 希区柯克的《西北偏北》
在德国 它被相当合理地改名为《不可见的第三者》 等等
我的第三个例子 对不起 我不能克制自己不讲糟糕的种族主义笑话
你知道 对巴西人来说 我和你谈过
葡萄牙人是愚蠢的
想法是 所有聪明的葡萄牙人都去了巴西 那里留下的都是白痴
所以你知道希区柯克的《精神病患者》的故事吗
巴西的笑话是 《精神病患者》在葡萄牙的标题被改成了“他自己是自己的母亲” 以使其易于理解
所以沿着这些线索 这次它有效果
标题是《信仰的阴谋》 一部2016年的丹麦电影 再次呼吁非法活动（下盗版）
你可以立即从Pirate Bay或其他地方下载它
我不会用故事来烦你 但我会给你看 只需一分钟 请准备好 一个四五分钟的剪辑
这是一个诚实警察的故事 他被描述为一个抑郁症晚期的人 总是绝望的
当然完全是80年代的 孩子们正在失踪 以一种奇怪的、虐待狂的方式被杀害
最后 侦探找到了凶手 他真的是一种理想的、帕西法尔式的雅利安人 长着蓝色的长发 一个病态的杀手 认为自己是恶魔的工具 恶魔的儿子
他的任务是 他说 摧毁父母的信仰
不仅仅是折磨孩子 而是他这样做是为了让父母在场或让父母意识到这一点
所以他说他的主要任务不仅仅是折磨和杀害人 而是以这样一种方式做 以至于它摧毁了他们的信仰
然后发生了一些道德上相当震撼的场景
我觉得它很美
不要太惊慌
如果你们中的一些人需要警告
可能会被震惊 因为一个孩子确实被淹死了
事实并非如此
在电影的结尾 他活了下来
他只是失去了知觉 所以这不会太过分
因为有些人在某次演讲中 当我展示这个时进行了抗议 你怎么能展示这个等等
不要这样
好的 现在让我们展示 我想我已经描述得足够多了
莫里塞特 莫斯科河
那里都是表演吗？
好的 停止
我认为即使是现在电影也失去了它的精神 因为好像在这种立场之后 你知道 上帝从外部介入
但无论如何 我的观点非常简单
从我的基督教无神论者的立场来看 不 那个杀手是错的
上帝出现了两次 当他 侦探 献出自己 说带走我 带走我 以及当那个女孩不想刺伤那个人时
所以这是我的疯狂立场
我会尽量简短 不会太啰嗦
买我的下一本书 在那里你将会读到所有关于这个主题的章节
它被称为《空虚的失禁》 将于10月由MIT出版社出版
这就是我所说的基督教无神论
基督并不是一个积极的救赎者的形象
而只是这个冷漠的凝视 它给予你准备去做 没有任何信仰中的保证
我不是以这种廉价的方式解读
那个家伙 侦探 认为自己是个无神论者 但实际上他是最深信不疑的人
他是
杀手是对的 （侦探是）最深信不疑的人
你知道 当杀手告诉他
我从未遇到过一个像你这样有信仰的人
但这正是因为他不需要任何更高力量的保证
他只是必须在一个完全没有希望的情况下去做
不是因为他想在天堂获得自己的位置
而是纯粹的神圣善良
你看到一个情况 你必须去做
不是因为你在算账 哦 如果我救了这个孩子
我欺骗我的妻子的行为会被原谅
我会得到一个（天堂中的）床位
这与那无关
那么好吧 为什么然后 现在你可以问我一个简单的问题
为什么我称这为基督教无神论？
为什么我不简单地说这是唯物主义伦理？
像这样 纯粹的善良 没有保证
在这里 当然 我是唯物主义者
这里没有误解
但我的好朋友 我真的很喜欢他
好吧 不是好朋友
我吹嘘
我夸大其词
我见过他两次
我们相处得非常好
你知道罗恩·威廉姆斯 左翼的坎特伯雷前大主教吗？
在他的陀思妥耶夫斯基书中--我不喜欢陀思妥耶夫斯基 但我喜欢他的书--威廉姆斯的陀思妥耶夫斯基
他在书中提供了我能想象到的最好的《白痴》解读之一 我不能克制不简短地向你描述这个
你知道 《白痴》的通常解读是 他对这个世界来说太神圣了 一个圣人
对于罗恩·威廉姆斯来说 这是一个奇妙的解读
而且这非常真实 如果你知道陀思妥耶夫斯基《白痴》的故事
他不是纯粹的邪恶 《白痴》的米什金王子 而是一种更加精致的东西
有些人 我见过他们 他们确实存在 他们真的是真诚的 无疑的 他们自身是善良的
但他们在他们的社会环境中的行为方式是一种错误的善良
他们绝对真诚地善良 但对他们四周造成了灾难
例如 米什金王子 他造成了什么？
纳斯塔西娅·菲利波芙娜被别人谋杀 或者 他在自己周围引发了灾难
罗恩·威廉姆斯在他关于陀思妥耶夫斯基的书中提供了一个关于神圣维度最基本形态的精彩定义
他提到了四位英国天主教小说家——奥康纳、珀西、斯帕克和埃利斯——并对他们作了这样的描述
所有四位都创造了一个世界 在这个世界里 世俗多数的观点被相对化了
但没有一个简单的替代方案 任何人都不能仅凭一个决定或一系列决定就进入其中 从这个世俗现实的意义上来说 这是糟糕的 必须有一个更高的秩序
这些小说的宗教维度在于一种持续的不协调感 即使小说内的任何人都无法说出我们应该与什么相协调 这种不协调感也是不可忽视的
所以 我们的世界就是脱节的、不一致的、缺少某些东西 但这实际上是负面神学 不是通常意义上的负面神学 即上帝是如此超越以至于我们无法恰当地描述他 不 它简单地就是 上帝就是这种缺席
这个空虚的位置出现在我们通过用上帝的形象来填补它之前
基本的神圣维度就是这个空虚 就是这个空虚 意味着我们的现实有着严重的问题
我认为 不仅我们可以以唯物主义的方式思考这个问题
而是我们只能以唯物主义的方式正确地思考这个问题
而这里的事情变得复杂了
我们应该拒绝马克思最著名的公式之一 即宗教是人民的鸦片
首先 要小心 马克思并没有说是（某些人）给人民的鸦片
这对马克思来说太粗俗了
不是像某种天真的启蒙形式那样
一些邪恶的神职人员像哥伦比亚的毒贩那样制造宗教 对不起 我的错 我很抱歉
不 它是人民的鸦片
但你知道我今天对这个公式的主要反对意见是什么吗？
是的 我们有一种宗教作为人民的鸦片发挥作用
当然 恐怖主义的原教旨宗教 但别忘了 不仅仅在穆斯林国家
我在这里是一个悲观主义者
你知道 在美国 FBI正在监视两百万名基督教原教旨主义者 怀疑他们可能是恐怖分子
很抱歉告诉你 这基本上和阿拉伯人中的比例一样 你知道
因此 问题不应该仅仅是伊斯兰恐惧症 而应该是在现代全球资本主义的辩证法中 是什么驱使人们走向原教旨主义
但好吧 这也许也是今天的宗教作为人民鸦片的一个版本
但至少还有两个 我认为阿多诺已经在某处提到了这个
我们有另外两种人民的鸦片
我希望你能猜到它们是什么
鸦片和人民
对民粹主义者来说 他们的鸦片就是人民本身
你知道这个幻想图像 人民 等等
玛丽娜·勒庞的鸦片是人民 等等
真正的法国人民受到威胁
另一种人民的鸦片就是鸦片
对许多知识分子来说 鸦片就是毒品
它就是鸦片 正如你所知
所以摆脱它的方式 我支持宗教维度 但以这种纯粹抽象的方式
我没有时间去做 可以以这种意义给出一个精彩的解读来联系 既然这些家伙是丹麦人 联系上显而易见的人物 克尔凯郭尔
他的宗教公式 当他说上帝与我们无关时 上帝正在与它自己相关 所有这些公式至少我认为接近某种非常悖论的唯物主义
我不想让你太厌烦 我希望你不要再次抗议我已经向你展示了太多的这种政治正确的疯狂行为
我的天啊 如果你 我 你知道 也当我谈论强奸时 人们声称你不应该用这么生动的术语或者什么来谈论 你知道 那是令人震惊的
见鬼 它应该是令人震惊的 你知道 因为如果你只是抽象地描述它
那么它真的不会影响你 那就只是 哦 它就像官僚统计数据一样 你知道
不 你应该被正在发生的恐怖事情震惊
非常感谢你们的耐心倾听